(ハゴロモ)名を ハゴロモ。
My name is Hagoromo…
As the founder of Ninshu,
the Ninja Creed…
忍宗の開祖にして
六道仙人ともいう。
I am also known as
The Sage of the Six Paths.
(柱間)あなたが六道仙人!?
You're The Sage of
the Six Paths?
いかにも。
Indeed I am.
今 ナルトとサスケは
アシュラとインドラの魂を引き継ぎ→
Right now, Naruto and
Sasuke have taken on
Ashura and Indra's souls and
are battling my mother Kaguya…
我が母 カグヤと戦っている。
Ashura?
アシュラ!?
たしか 今 私を前任者と…。
You just called me
the "previous reincarnate"?
Yes…
そうだ。 アシュラとインドラは
わしの２人の息子…。
Ashura and Indra are my two sons.
そして 今 戦っている カグヤは
わしの母だ。
And Kaguya, the one who's
fighting right now, is my mother.
なんと！
What?!
So Ashura and Indra's souls
are connected to you too.
アシュラとインドラの魂は
お前にも関係のあることだ。
(ハゴロモ)
２つの魂は転生を繰り返し➡
Their souls have transmigrated
over and over again.
以前 アシュラの魂は お前に…。
The soul of Ashura was
previously inside you,
インドラの魂は
マダラに宿っていたのだからな。
and Indra's soul was inside Madara.
(柱間)私に!?
Inside of me?!
Mother took advantage
of their souls,
(ハゴロモ)母上は ２人の魂を利用し→
and after an extraordinary
length of time,
途方もない時間を使って
よみがえったのだ。
she was resurrected.
今 わしには
マダラにとりついていた→
Right now, I know everything,
even the intentions of
the one called Zetsu,
ゼツと名のる 母上の第３の息子の
意思まで すべて わかる。
my mother's third son
who possessed Madara.
In order to save
Naruto and Sasuke,
ナルトとサスケを救うには➡
you, too, must know everything
that has occurred.
お前たちも
すべてを知る必要があるのだ。
Before I talk about
Ashura and Indra,
アシュラとインドラの話をするには➡
まず 忍宗の起源から
話さねばなるまい。
I must first explain the origin
of Ninshu, the Ninja Creed.
(ハゴロモ)時は 数千年の昔。
It was a few thousand years ago…
My younger brother Hamura and I,
わしと 弟のハムラは
母上のカグヤと十尾を月に封印した。
sealed our mother Kaguya and
the Ten Tails in the moon.
そして ハムラは 母上を見張るため
月へと渡っていったのだ。
Hamura went to the moon as well,
so he could watch over Mother.
Ninshu: The Ninja Creed
((ハゴロモ : 世話になったな ガマ丸。
Thank you for your help, Gamamaru.
(ハゴロモ)お前に教えてもらった
仙力がなければ→
Without the Sage Power
that you taught me,
母上は倒せなかった。
we couldn't have defeated Mother.
You insist on leaving, sibling?
(ガマ丸)どうしても行くのか 兄弟。
Yes. There is something I must do.
あぁ。 私には
やらねばならぬことが ある。
(ガマ丸)何をするつもりじゃ？
What are you going to do?
(ハゴロモ)旅の目的は ２つ。
My journey will have two purposes.
１つは 十尾から分けた
９匹の尾獣の住みかを探すことだ。
The first…
To find a dwelling place for each
of the nine Tailed Beasts
that I extracted from
the Ten Tails.
この連中が
互いに ケンカをせぬよう➡
I want to make sure
they don't fight amongst each other…
その力が人々に悪用されぬよう→
and that people don't use
their powers for evil.
I intend to choose
their homes very carefully.
慎重に故郷を見定めようと思う。
２つ目の目的は→
The second purpose is to
restore this ravaged land.
この荒れ果てた地上を
復元することだ。
In our battles against Mother,
母上との戦いで 私たちは
地上に莫大な傷を残してしまった。
we caused terrible damage
to the land.
I must atone for this crime.
私は その罪を
償わなければならない。
そうか…。
I see.
そうじゃのう
それが いいかもしれん。
Yes, that might be good to do.
But the road ahead will be difficult.
だが 道は厳しいぞ。
わかっている。
I am aware of that.
実は 昨日 夢をみた。
夢？
You know,
I had a dream last night.
A dream?
ガマは めったに夢をみぬ。
Toads rarely dream.
When they do dream,
it always comes true.
みた夢は 必ず現実となる。
ガマの夢は運命じゃからのう。
Because a toad's dream
is destiny.
What did you dream?
どんな夢だ？
遠い未来に ９匹のケダモノの名を呼び
たわむれる 碧眼の少年が現れる。
Far into the future,
a blue-eyed youth will appear,
who will amuse himself with
the names of the nine beasts.
その子が奇跡を呼び起こす夢じゃ。
I dreamed that
he will call forth a miracle.
再び 乱世が
やってくるというのか？
Does that mean there will be
another age of discord?
わからぬ。
I do not know.
Will everything I do from now on,
be meaningless?
では 私が
これから やることも ムダか？
気にする必要は ない。
Don't worry.
避けようと思って 避けられるのは
運命などでは ないからのう。
Fate is something
you cannot escape.
お前は お前の道をいくとええ。
Go on your way.
縁があったら
また会おうぞ 兄弟。
And if fate wills it,
our paths shall cross again, sibling.
うむ さらばだ。
Farewell.
どうやら１つ目の試練のようだな。
I guess this is my first test.
Huh?
(フタミ)おい おい おい おい
何してんだ？
Hey, hey, hey, hey!
What are you doing?
橋を直すのさ。
I'm going to fix the bridge.
は？ お前
なに余計なことしてんだよ。
What?
Why do something uncalled for?
なぜ余計だ？
橋はみんなにとって必要なはずだ。
How is it "uncalled for"?
The bridge is essential
to everyone.
みんなにとって必要だから
俺には あっちゃ困るのよ。
Everyone needs it.
That's why it's a problem
for me if it's there.
ほう おもしろいことを言うな。
Oh… An interesting comment.
いいか この橋が壊れてるから→
Listen, because the bridge
is broken,
みんな ここで立ち止まる
そこで俺の出番だ。
everyone stops right here.
That's where I come in.
そいつのもとに行って
俺がこの川を→
I go over to the guy
and take his belongings
無事に渡してあげましょうと
荷物を預かる。
and offer to help him cross.
そしたら すたこらさっさと
逃げちまうのさ。
Then, without a moment's hesitation,
I make my getaway
with his stuff.
こう見えても
足には自信があるんだ。
I may not look fast,
but these legs never fail me.
それが俺の商売よ。
This is what I do for a living.
フフ なるほど お前は
この壊れた橋で食っている→
I see.
So you're a thief that uses
this broken bridge to make a living.
泥棒というわけか。
そうよ。
That's right.
So just leave well enough alone.
だから 余計なことされると
困るのさ。
だが 橋を直して
困るのは お前一人だ。
But it only benefits you.
多くの人は困らない。
It's a hardship for everyone else.
Hey! I said leave it alone.
Do you understand me?
てめえ やめろって言ってんのが
わからねえのか。
うっ…。
なんで お前
そんなことするんだよ？
Why are you going through
all that trouble?
私は罪を償っている。
This is to atone for my sins.
お前 罪人なのか？
So are you a criminal?
似たようなものだ。
Something like that.
なんだ この橋は渡れないのか。
Oh man, I guess can't
cross the bridge.
旦那 お困りのようですね。
Mister, you seem to be in a bind.
ですが あっしに任せてくれれば
川の向こうへお渡ししますぜ。
Leave it to me,
I'll take you to
the other side of the river.
おぉ。
よすのだな。
- Oh!
- I wouldn't, if I were you.
その男は泥棒だ。
なっ…。
That man's a thief.
What?!
俺をバカにするな。
Don't take me for a fool!
おい てめえ！
人の商売の邪魔するんじゃねえ。
Hey, you!
Quit messing with my business!
チッ…。
私は この橋を直すまで
ここを動かん。
I'm not moving until
I fix this bridge.
別の橋に行ったほうがいいぞ。
You should go find
another bridge.
バカ言え 俺たちにも縄張り
ってもんがあるんだよ。
Don't be stupid!
Thieves like me have
our own territory…
他のとこになんて行けるか。
I can't just go somewhere else.
では どうせなら
手伝ったらどうだ？
Well then,
why don't you help me?
橋が完成すれば 私はよそへ行く。
I'll leave once the bridge
is finished.
ふざけたこと言ってんじゃねえ！
Quit messing around!
そうか ではしかたない。
I see.
Then there's nothing more to say.
そこで橋が直るまで待つのだな。
You can wait until
the bridge is fixed.
うぉっ…。
チクショウ こうなったら邪魔して…。
Damn it!
Fine, I'll just get in his way…
う～ん！
あの野郎…。
That bastard…
どんなバカ力してやがんだ。
Just where does that
brute strength come from?
あ～ もう！
Damn it!
(フタミ)おい しっかりしやがれ！
Hey! Get it together!
急がねえと せっかく集めた材木が
流されちまうぞ！
We've got to work fast or the logs
you went to great lengths to gather
will just get washed away.
ほう 手伝ってくれるのか。
Oh…
You're going to help me?
俺はさっさと あんたに
どっかに行ってもらいたいんだ！
I just want you to go away
as soon as possible.
橋ができたら 俺が
ぶっ壊してやる！
And once the bridge is done,
I'm gonna destroy it.
フフッ。
私の名前は ハゴロモだ。
My name is Hagoromo.
(俺は フタミだ。
よろしくな フタミ))
And I'm Futami.
Nice to meet you, Futami.
((イテッ！
何やってんだよ？
Ouch!
What are you doing?
Can't you tell?
見てわかんねえのか？
橋をつくってんだよ。
I'm building a bridge!
You're a thief, right?
お前 泥棒だろ？
そんなことしても→
Doing that won't make all
the bad stuff you did go away!
悪さしたことは消えないぞ！
うるせえ！
Shut up! Get lost, brat!
どっか行け このガキ！
ハハハ これでお前も
私と同じだな。
Now, you're just like me.
I'm not like you.
同じなもんか。
俺は罪を償ってるわけじゃねえ。
I'm not doing this
for atonement.
I'm telling you…
橋ができたら
絶対にぶっ壊してやる！
When it's done,
I'm gonna destroy it.
やっと３分の１かよ。
All that work and we're only
one-third of the way done…
壊すのは簡単だが
つくるのは骨が折れる。
Breaking it apart is easy,
but building it back up
is backbreaking work.
こんだけ丈夫につくり直せば
そう簡単には壊れないぜ。
Something this sturdy
won't be easy to break.
That's true.
If we make it too sturdy…
そうだな だが
あまり頑丈につくりすぎると→
お前が壊すときに
骨が折れるぞ。
you'll break your bones for sure
when you try to destroy it.
え？ ヘヘ。
Hey you! Don't touch those logs!
おい コラ
かっぱらうんじゃねえ！
We're using 'em to fix the bridge!
そいつは橋をつくる
材料なんだからな！
俺たちも手伝います。
We'll help you.
え？
だって俺たちが使う橋ですから。
Huh?
Since we're going to be
the ones using the bridge.
ったく 危なっかしいなあ。
You gotta be careful.
もっと小さいのにしろ。
うん。
Just grab a smaller one.
Okay!
It's finished!
We did it! We did it!
やった やった やった～！
The bridge is finished!
橋が完成したぞ！ アハハ！
うお～ すげえ！
This is awesome!
完成したな。
It's done, eh?
壊しがいのある橋だ。
A bridge worth the effort to destroy.
Are you kidding me?!
何言ってんだ
こんな苦労してつくったのに→
After all the work we put into it,
there's no way I'd destroy it.
ぶっ壊せるわけねえだろ！
ハハハ！
お前は よいことをしたな。
You did a good thing.
私は新たな地へ
向かうときがきたようだ。
And it's time for me to move on
to a new place.
達者でな フタミ。
Take care of yourself, Futami.
おい 待ってくれよ！
俺も一緒に行くよ。
Hey, wait up!
I'm coming with you!
Oh?
ほう あの橋が
お前の住みかではないのか？
I thought that bridge
was where you lived.
あんな立派な橋が出来たんじゃ
俺の商売は あがったりだぜ。
With an awesome bridge
like that,
my business is shot to hell!
よき行いをすると
人々に感謝されて気分がいい。
When you do a good deed,
people are grateful and
it's a good feeling.
そして気分がよくなるために
更に よいことをする。
And because it feels good,
you do more good deeds.
それが よき行いの輪廻だ。
That's the cycle of goodness.
確かに… そう言われればそうだ。
When you put it that way…
you're right.
あんた いいこと言うな。
You have a way with words.
そういや
ずっと聞けなかったけど→
By the way,
I didn't ask you before, but…
あんた いったい何者なんだ？
Who are you anyway?
私はかつて
この世界をめちゃくちゃにした。
I once wreaked havoc
upon this world.
何年か前に あっちこっちで→
Several years ago,
there were many occurrences
大津波や大噴火が
立て続けにあったけど→
of giant tsunami and
volcanic eruptions here and there.
まさか それが
あんたのせいだっていうのか？
Don't tell me you caused them?
そんなことが
人にできるわけねえだろ。
Come on, there's no way
one person could've done that!
それに そんな力があるなら→
Besides, if you were that strong,
さっさと
橋を直せばいいじゃねえか。
you could've fixed that
bridge in an instant,
あんなに汗水流さなくても。
instead of working and
sweating so hard.
私はもう
余計な力は使わぬと決めた。
I decided never to use
excessive power again.
そうでなければ
人々の心はわからぬ。
Otherwise, I wouldn't be able
to understand how people feel.
手を出してみろ。
え？
Put your hand out.
何だこれ… 力が湧いてくる。
What is this?
I feel power surging into me.
今 お前に力を渡したのだ。
力？
I just passed my power to you.
Power?
そうだな チャクラとでも呼ぼうか。
Yes…
Or maybe I should say chakra.
いわば 人と人をつなぐ力だ。
It is, so to speak, the power to
connect people to each other.
そういうものであってほしいと
私は願っている。
That's the kind of power
I want it to be.
俺は それをもらったのか？
And you passed it on to me?
そうだ だが誰にでも
分け与えられるものではない。
Yes. But it's not something
I can give to just anyone.
お前の心が私に近くなったからだ。
I've come to feel
very close to you.
お前は善の心を知ったのだ。
You have learned
what a good heart is.
何のマネだ？
What are you doing?
俺を あんたの弟子にしてくれ。
Please, make me your apprentice!
弟子だと？
あぁ。
My apprentice?
Yeah!
あんたには
何か特別なものを感じる。
I feel something very special
in you…
俺は ずっと
つまらない人生を生きてきた。
I've lived a meaningless life.
何の価値もねえ人生だ。
だけど あんたは違う。
My entire life's been worthless!
But you're different.
あんたは きっと
大きなことを成し遂げる人だ。
You're someone who
can do great things!
だから あんたといれば
俺のチンケな人生も→
So…if I stay with you,
maybe my insignificant life will
start to show a little value.
ちょっとくらい
価値が出ると思うんだ。
人の役に立ちたくなったか。
So you want to be helpful
to others now?
あの橋をつくったことは→
When we finished that bridge…
あのとき
喜んでくれた人たちの笑顔は→
All those happy people
and their smiles…
俺の生涯の誇りだ。
I've never been prouder
in my whole life.
あのときの
みんなの顔が忘れられねえ。
I'll never forget the look
on their faces!
きっとそれが あんた…
いえ ハゴロモ様の言った絆だ。
I'm positive that that's the bond
that you spoke of…
I mean, Master Hagoromo.
お前は私に
大きなことを教えてくれた。
You just taught me something
very important.
私の旅には もう１つ
大きな目的ができたようだ。
I think my journey has found
another important purpose.
３つ目の目的
チャクラによる人々の絆だ。
A third purpose.
People bonding through chakra.
(ミツオ)旦那 旦那
橋が壊れててお困りでしょう。
Mister, hey Mister!
You in a bind because
the bridge is broken?
あっしが向こう側へ渡る方法を…。
I can help you cross
to the other side…
お前 なんで こんなところに!?
Hey, you!
What are you doing here?!
ここは俺の縄張りだぞ！
This is my turf!
今から この橋をつくり直すぞ。
We're going to rebuild this bridge!
は？ なに言ってんだ この野郎。
Huh? What the hell are you saying?
いいから！ 今日から
お前も善人になるんだよ。
Listen up!
From today, you're gonna
become a good person!
お前 頭おかしくなったのか？
Did you hit your head
or something?
(フフフフ… ハハハハハハハ！))
(ハゴロモ)やがて 徐々にだが
人々の中にも→
In time, albeit slowly…
I found people who understood
my way of thinking.
わしの考えを
理解しようとする者たちが現れた。
その中には わしとともに
人々のために→
And some among them joined me
on my journey to help people.
一緒に旅をしてくれる者たちまで
現れるようになった。
この頃から わしは
その者たちを弟子とし→
From around this time,
I made them my apprentices…
自分のチャクラを分け与えていった。
and passed on my chakra.
そして その絆を わしたちは
忍宗と名付けた。
I named this bond
"Ninshu, the Ninja Creed."
わしは弟子たちとともに修業し
考え続けた。
I trained with my apprentices…
and continued to ponder…
命とは何か。 愛とは何か。
What is life? What is love?
力とは何なのかを。
What is power?
わしたちは いつか
チャクラでできる人の絆が→
We believed that someday, this bond
with people through chakra
世界を平和に導くと信じたのだ。
NINSHU
would lead to world peace.
わしたちの旅は果てしなく続いた。
We continued our travels
for a long time.
途方もなく荒れ果てた地を
直しながら…。
Restoring places that were
nearly destroyed for no reason…
(ハゴロモ)そして その中で→
And when we found a place
in those areas
尾獣たちを解放するための
場所を見つけては➡
where we could release
the Tailed Beasts,
そこに
監視のための祠をつくった。
we built a shrine for the purpose
of guarding them.
(ハゴロモ)弟子たちの多くは→
Many of my pupils scattered
to different regions
荒れ地を
わしの代わりに修復するため➡
to repair the land in my place.
各地へと散っていった。
こうして忍宗は
世界の各地に広まっていったのだ。
And in this manner, Ninshu,
the Ninja Creed, spread to
each corner of the world.
その後 わしは 死の間際→
And later, on my deathbed,
自分の中にいた尾獣たちを
彼らの故郷に放った。
I sent the Tailed Beasts that had been
inside me to their respective lands.
彼らが平穏に暮らせる日々が
やってくることを祈りながら。
Praying that they would be able
to spend their days in peace…
((私は もう長くない。
I will not live much longer…
守鶴 又旅 磯撫 孫悟空→
Shukaku, Matatabi, Isobu,
Son Goku, Kokuo,
穆王 犀犬 重明→
Saiken, Chomei, Gyuki, and Kurama…
牛鬼 九喇嘛。
離れていても
お前たちはいつも一緒だ。
Even if you are far apart,
you will always be together.
いずれ一つになるときが来よう。
And eventually,
there will come a time
when you will be united again.
それぞれの名を持ち
今までとは違う形でな。
Each of you with a unique name…
and a different form
than before.
そして 私の中にいたときと違い
正しく導かれる。
And unlike when
you were inside of me,
you will be guided down
the right path.
本当の力とは何か。
I hope you learn
what true strength is…
(そのときまで))
before that time…
(ハゴロモ)しかし
お前たちも知ってのとおり→
But as you know,
contrary to my hopes…
わしの思いとは裏腹に→
Throughout this long history,
men appeared one after another,
長い歴史の中で尾獣たちの力を➡
with the desire to use
Tailed Beasts for evil purposes…
悪用しようとする者たちが
次々と現れ→
彼らは人間に
愛想をつかしてしまうのだが…。
which turned the Tailed Beasts
against mankind.
話を戻そう。
Anyway, back to my story.
わしたちは 長い旅を続け→
We continued our long journey.
ようやく３つの目的が
ひと段落し→
When at last,
I fulfilled my three goals,
村に戻ったわしは
その地を忍宗の総本山とした。
I returned to my village
and made it the headquarters
of Ninshu.
わしは そこで妻をめとり
２人の子供を授かった。
I married and fathered two sons.
それが インドラとアシュラだ。
They were Indra and Ashura.
アシュラを産んでから ２人の母は
産後の肥立ちが悪く→
Their mother had a difficult recovery
after giving birth to Ashura…
まもなく この世を去った。
and she passed away
shortly after.
しかし
２人の息子は元気に育った。
But my two sons grew up
strong and healthy.
２人は仲のよい兄弟だった。
They were close siblings.
兄は常に弟を思い→
The older one was especially caring
弟は常に 兄の背を追いかけた。
and the younger one was always
chasing after his brother.
(ハゴロモ)だが わしは このとき
まだ気づいていなかった。
But at the time, I didn't realize
息子たちを利用しようと→
that a dark force
was already at work
すでに闇の力が
うごめきはじめていたことに。
trying to manipulate my sons…
At the time,
my Ninshu did not have
a practical application for fighting yet.
My original intent for it was
to